The James B. Preston MD Collection
Archives and Special Collections at the SUNY Upstate Health Sciences Library
The James B. Preston MD Collection
1951-2004
SUNY Upstate Medical University 766 Irving Avenue Syracuse, NY 13210
Preston, James B.
2.5 linear feet
This collection contains the papers of James B. Preston, who was a Professor of Physiology at SUNY Upstate Medical University in Syracuse, NY. The collection has five series: Subject Files, Photographs, Printed Materials, Lectures, and Correspondence.
2008.0002
Biographical Note
Dr. James B. Preston (1926-2004) was a renowned neurophysiologist. Dr. Preston attended Ohio Wesleyan University from 1944-1945. His education was interrupted by military service. He served in Korea from 1945-1947 as a member of the Army Signal Corps and then as a medic stationed on the 38th parallel. When he returned, he attended Ohio Wesleyan for another year and then enrolled at the University of Cincinnati College of Medicine where he received his M.D. in 1952. He spent the next two years in a combined internship-research fellowship at the University of Illinois College of Medicine. In 1954 Dr. Preston was hired as an instructor at the SUNY Upstate Medical University, and in 1956 he was named an assistant professor at Upstate. In 1960 at the age of 34, he was promoted to a full professor and chairman of the Department of Physiology where he remained for 31 years before he retired in 1991. In 1992 he became a professor emeritus at the SUNY Upstate Medical University.
Dr. Preston’s scientific research centered on investigations into the neural basis of the control of movement. His contributions to neurophysiology are fundamental to our concepts of how the brain controls movement. Over the course of his career, he published over 40 research based articles in his field. His research was continuously funded by the National Institute of Health for over thirty-two years. Many of his graduate students and postdoctoral students went on to distinguished academic careers in the area of neural science. For over forty years, medical students benefited from his instruction. Preston served on numerous national and state committees including: Chairman, Physical and Molecular Biology Evaluation Conference-NIH, DRG (1968); Chairman, Physiology Training Committee-NIGMS,NIH (1971-1973); Chairman, Working Group on Pharmacology, National Advisory Committee on Multiple Sclerosis-USPHS (1973-1974); President, Association of Chairs of Departments of Physiology (1973-1974); Chairman, Subcommittee on Chemotherapeutic Agents, National Multiple Sclerosis Society (1975- 1980); Chairman, Sponsored Research Advisory Committee, Research Foundation, SUNY (1982-1986); Conference Chair, Winter Conference on Brain Research (1987-1988); Director, Winter Conference on Brain Research (1989-1991).
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the papers of James B. Preston, who was a Professor of Physiology at SUNY Upstate Medical University in Syracuse, NY. There are five series in this collection.
Subject Files: these documents include newspaper clippings, photographs, press releases, and newsletters from the 1950s to 1990s in addition to VHS and DVD recordings of the 2004 memorial ceremony for Dr. Preston. The folders with Dr. Preston’s notes include photocopies of scholarly publications with Dr. Preston’s handwritten notes and comments on the articles.
Photographs: these materials from the 1950s to 1990s contain group photographs of his department and academic organizations, 2 boxes of Polaroid slide mounts with research information, tables, and figures, and portrait photographs of Dr. Preston, including one photograph of him with Donald Kennedy, who was the commissioner of the FDA during the Carter Administration.
Printed Materials: this series has two folders with published articles that Dr. Preston contributed to or was featured in from 1956 and 1988.
Lectures: this series primarily contains Dr. Preston’s lecture materials from the 1960s to 1990s, which include slides, typed and manuscript notes and drafts of lectures, index cards with references, correspondence, and print publications with notes, figures, and images. The folders on the Carlyle F. Jacobsen lecture series from 1966 and the 1980s include correspondence, biographical information, newspaper clippings, press releases, publicity materials, print photographs, slides, notes, and photocopies of articles by Dr. Jacobsen.
Correspondence: these documents concern Dr. Preston’s career, research, and publications from the 1950s to 1980s. Some related materials are included with the letters, such as newsletters, newspaper clippings, reports, and lecture notes.
Arrangement of the Collection
The James B. Preston MD Collection has been arranged into five series.
Subject and Genre Headings
Preston, James B.; Neurology; Neuropharmacology; Neurophysiology; Neuroscience; Pharmacology; Physiology; Medical Education; SUNY Upstate Medical University
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Acquisition Information
Gift of James B. Preston Jr. in 2008.
Inventory
- Subject Files
  - Appointment as Department of Physiology chairman, 1959-1960 (Box Box 1)
  - Barbara and James B. Preston endowment fund establishment article and list of donors, 2000 (Box Box 1)
  - Banquet honoring Dr. James B. Preston, 1993 (Box Box 1)
  - Curriculum vitaes, c. 1986; c. 1993 (Box Box 1)
  - Recordings of memorial ceremony for Dr. James B. Preston on VHS and DVD with list of speakers, 2004 (Box Box 1)
  - Comments by Dr. Peter Strick for Dr. James B. Preston portrait unveiling, 1996 (Box Box 1)
  - Publication copies and notes, c. 1970-1990; 6 folders (Box Boxes 1 and 2)
- Photographs
  - 1952, c. 1980 (Box Box 3)
  - c. 1952, 1966; c. 1968; c. 1980; 1981; 1989 (Box Box 3)
  - c. 1980, 1993 (Box Box 3)
  - Polaroid slide mounts and 35mm negatives with research information, tables, and figures, 1977-1978; c. 1987; 2 boxes and 1 folder (Box Box 3)
- Printed Materials
  - Scope Weekly featuring photograph of Drs. James B. Preston and Gordon K. Moe at the American Heart Association meeting, 1956 (Box Box 3)
  - “The Founding Years of the Winter Conference on Brain Research: A History of the WCBR Commemorating the Twentieth Anniversary” with a preface by chairperson James B. Preston, 1988 (Box Box 3)
- Lectures
  - Carlyle F. Jacobsen lecture series, 1966; 1982-1989; 3 folders (Box Box 3)
  - Emerging insights into the motor representations of the primate frontal lobe, 1980-1982; 1987 (Box Box 4)
  - Sensors in inner ear images, undated (Box Box 4)
  - Motor units and spinal reflexes from Richard P. Dum, 1997 (Box Box 4)
  - Antipyretic increase in secretion, G-I drugs, c. 1960 (Box Box 4)
  - Cortex-double representations seminar KSU, Emerging Insights into the Motor Representations of the Primate Frontal Lobe, 1983 (Box Box 4)
  - Evidence for a Transcortical Reflex: Primate Corticospinal Tract Neuron Responses to Ramp Stretch of Muscle, T. Sakai, 1978 (Box Box 4)
  - Stretch reflex, feedback, and motor cortex notes, c. 1975 (Box Box 4)
  - Premotor-motor notes, 1984 (Box Box 4)
  - The Premotor Area of Primates: A Historical Perspective, 1985 (Box Box 4)
  - Frontal lobe and primate premotor cortex notes and figures, undated (Box Box 4)
  - Introduction to cardiovascular system, general organization, 1991 (Box Box 4)
  - Seminars: spindle MC, MC spinal reflex, undated (Box Box 4)
  - Remembrances of things past, spasticity, posture, 1988 (Box Box 5)
  - History, motor cortex, lecture I, 1982-1983 (Box Box 5)
  - Seminar: A New Concept of Input-Output Organization for the Primate Motor Cortex, 1985; 1988 (Box Box 5)
  - Frequency of simulation and neuromuscular blocking agents notes and figures, undated (Box Box 5)
  - Posture and spasticity, 1994-1998 (Box Box 5)
  - Monitoring and regulation of movements, 1994-1999 (Box Box 5)
  - Vestibular lecture, 1992 (Box Box 5)
  - Corticospinal tract inhibition in postural adjustments, 1985 (Box Box 6)
  - Japanese congress of neurological surgeons, monday address, 1986 (Box Box 6)
  - History on neuromuscular junctions, undated (Box Box 6)
  - Neuroscience introduction, history, 1988 (Box Box 6)
  - Sherrington, undated (Box Box 6)
  - Pyramidal motor I and II, undated (Box Box 6)
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1951-1959 (Box Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1964; 1967-1969 (Box Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 1970; 1976; 1978; 1980; 1982-1983 (Box Box 6)